<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Development Process</title>
    <author email="bob@eng.werken.com">bob mcwhirter</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="Development Process">

    <subsection name="General">
      <p>
      All projects from The Werken Company start with an attitude
      of openess and communication.  This is followed by the
      attitudes of consistency and excellence.  Sub-par code
      is never a good thing.  We are dedicated to writing
      well-documented and well-tested code.  Communication
      through <a href="mail-lists.html">mailling lists</a>,
      <a href="irc.html">IRC</a>, and 
      <a href="http://blogs.werken.com/people/bob/">blogs</a>
      work to keep interested parties apprised of the project's
      progress.
      </p>

      <p>
      A lightweight development process similar to SCRUM is used
      to organize feature sprints.  Loose coordination amongst
      master developers guides the direction of the project.  Input
      from users is catered to when it serves the global vision
      of the project.
      </p>

      <p>
      Anyone wishing to contribute thoughts, ideas, opinions or
      code are welcomed.  If a contributor consistently provides
      valuable input he will be offered the opportunity to become
      a full-fledged developer with complete access to the project.
      </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Standards">
      <p>
      Where <b>sensible</b>, the project should adhere to 
      applicable standards.  Standards <b>should not</b> be
      blindly followed, but rather excellent solutions should
      be found to each problem.  While being standards-compliant
      has its place, there will always be a need for solutions
      that are better than merely standard.
      </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Equality, Respect and Ownership">
      <p> 
      While we do not directly promote <b>code ownership</b>, we 
      recognize each developer's proficiencies and 
      experience.  We do try to promote cross-developer
      interaction and knowledge so as to reduce the 
      bus-factor for the code.  Without true code ownership,
      though, all developers are free to work on any part
      of the project.  Just show respect and don't step
      on anyone's blue suede shoes.
      </p> 

    </subsection>

  </section>

</body>
</document>

