<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Release Process</title>
    <author email="matt@indigoegg.com">Matt Ho</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="Release Process">

  <subsection name="...Checklist...">
  <p>
    The following actions should be performed when releasing a new version of drools.  
  </p>
  <p>
    After deploying the release, take a few moments to verify that the files were all
    posted as expected.  Verify that the new release does download from the links 
    provided.
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="...Checklist...">
  <ol>
    <li>Send email to the development mailing list announcing a version control freeze for tagging.</li>
    <li>Check out fresh working copy of CVS module you're going to tag.</li>
    <li>
      Convert all SNAPSHOT jars in project.xml to concrete timestamped or versioned jar references.
    </li>
    <li>
      Ensure that build.xml agrees with project.xml with respect to dependent jars names.
    </li>
    <li>
      Update xdocs/releases.xml to reflect the current build version.
    </li>
    <li>
      Set the release version number in Maven project.xml . For 
      example, 2.0-beta-9-dev would become 2.0-beta-9
    </li>
    <li>
      Perform a successful build and test suite execution, and run the clean target to remove 
      any generated files using maven.  Repeat this process using ant.
    </li>
    <li>
      Commit your changes to the version control repository.
    </li>
    <li>
      Tag the release via cvs -q tag PROJECT_VERSION_MODIFIER . An example release tag is 
      DROOLS_2_0_BETA_9 .
    </li>
    <li>
      Deploy the drools maven-generated project site.
    </li>
    <li>
      Set the next development version number in Maven project.xml and/or Ant default.properties 
      and commit the change to the version control repository. For example, 2.0-beta-9 would become
      2.0-beta-10-dev
    </li>
    <li>
      Send email to the development mailing list announcing completion of the tag.
    </li>
  </ol>
  </subsection>

  </section>

</body>
</document>

