<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE connector PUBLIC '-//Sun Microsystems, Inc.//DTD Connector 1.0//EN' 'http://java.sun.com/j2ee/dtds/connector_1_0.dtd'>

<connector>

   <display-name>Drools Rule Engine Adaptor</display-name>
   <vendor-name>Werken Company</vendor-name>
   <spec-version>1.0</spec-version>
   <eis-type>Rule Engine</eis-type>
   <version>1.0</version>

   <license>
      <license-required>false</license-required>
      <description>
         COPYRIGHT AND PERMISSION NOTICE

         Copyright 2002 (C) The Werken Company. All Rights Reserved.

         Redistribution and use of this software and associated documentation
         ("Software"), with or without modification, are permitted provided
         that the following conditions are met:

         1. Redistributions of source code must retain copyright
            statements and notices.  Redistributions must also contain a
            copy of this document.

         2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the
            above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
            following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other
            materials provided with the distribution.

         3. The name "drools" must not be used to endorse or promote
            products derived from this Software without prior written
            permission of The Werken Company.  For written permission,
            please contact bob@werken.com.

         4. Products derived from this Software may not be called "drools"
            nor may "drools" appear in their names without prior written
            permission of The Werken Company. "drools" is a registered
            trademark of The Werken Company.

         5. Due credit should be given to The Werken Company.
            (http://drools.werken.com/).

         THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE WERKEN COMPANY AND CONTRIBUTORS
         ``AS IS'' AND ANY EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT
         NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
         FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
         THE WERKEN COMPANY OR ITS CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT,
         INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
         (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR
         SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION)
         HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT,
         STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE)
         ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED
         OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
      </description>
   </license>

   <resourceadapter>
      <managedconnectionfactory-class>org.drools.jsr94.jca.spi.RuleManagedConnectionFactory</managedconnectionfactory-class>
      <connectionfactory-interface>javax.resource.cci.ConnectionFactory</connectionfactory-interface>
      <connectionfactory-impl-class>org.drools.jsr94.jca.spi.RuleConnectionFactory</connectionfactory-impl-class>

      <transaction-support>NoTransaction</transaction-support>

      <authentication-mechanism>
         <authentication-mechanism-type>BasicPassword</authentication-mechanism-type>
         <credential-interface>javax.resource.security.PasswordCredential</credential-interface>
      </authentication-mechanism>
      <reauthentication-support>false</reauthentication-support>

   </resourceadapter>
</connector>
